Guide to the Archival Buildings File 1894-2005
University of Chicago Library
Archival Buildings File
1894-present
12 linear feet (24 boxes)
Hanna Holborn Gray Special Collections Research Center University of Chicago Library 1100 East 57th Street Chicago, Illinois 60637 U.S.A.
The Archival Buildings File was established in order to provide a means of organizing information and ephemeral materials relating to University buildings and making them more readily accessible.
Information on Use
Access
The collection is open for research
Scope Note
ARCHIVAL BUILDINGS FILE
The Archival Buildings File was established in order to provide a means of organizing information and ephemeral materials relating to University buildings and making them more readily accessible. Many items are received by the Archives concerning the history, architecture, and use of various buildings and structures on campus, which do not have a place in other record groups.
The first part of the file contains materials concerning campus architecture in general, including guides and maps, articles, and souvenir booklets with pictures of buildings and campus scenes. Following these are folders for individual buildings, arranged alphabetically. Among the items that can be found are programs for groundbreaking ceremonies, cornerstone layings, and dedications, as well as promotional brochures, press releases, and articles and reports from various sources. The files sometimes include correspondence and other information concerning the design, construction, remodeling, and architectural decoration of the buildings. Since some buildings have been known by more than one name, patrons should check the listing for all possible headings relating to their subject of inquiry.
Materials are added to the files as they are received. The listing and file arrangement are provisional and subject to change as additions and updates are made.
Photographs of University buildings are located in Series II of the Archival Photographic Files. These include not only exterior and interior shots but also photo-reproductions of architects' drawings and photographs of construction sequences. There is a separate Postcard Collection which features images of campus buildings and scenes. The Archives also maintains a substantial collection of architectural drawings and blueprints of many buildings on campus. Other information on buildings can be found in various University publications, and in the records of the Department of Buildings and Grounds, the Presidents' Papers, the Harold Swift Papers, and minutes of the Board of Trustees and its committees. Files on particular buildings can be found in other record groups as well. Please consult a member of the archival staff for more information.
Related Resources
Browse finding aids by topic.
Subject Headings
University of Chicago -- History; University of Chicago -- Buildings; Architecture -- Illinois -- Chicago -- History; Building -- Illinois -- Chicago -- History; College buildings -- Illinois -- Chicago
INVENTORY
- Series I: General
  - Architectural information and guides, general (Box 1)
  - Architectural information and guides, "A Prospective Student's Guide to the College of the University of Chicago with a Walking Tour of the Quadrangles," 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Architectural information and guides, "An Informational Guide to the University of Chicago," ca. 1966 (Box 1)
  - Architectural information and guides, Architectural Guide, building descriptions, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Architectural information and guides, worksheets, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Architectural information and guides, "The Tour," by Laura Koenig, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Architectural information and guides, "Campus Tour," by Greg Jao, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Articles on campus architecture, general, 1 (Box 2)
  - Articles on campus architecture, general, 2 (Box 2)
  - Articles on campus architecture, 1920s building program (Box 2)
  - Articles on campus architecture, property ownership and development (Box 2)
  - Articles on campus architecture, landscaping (Box 2)
  - Articles on campus architecture, "A Review of Planning at the University of Chicago 1891-1978" (Box 2)
  - Articles on campus architecture, Charles E. Jenkins, "The University of Chicago," in Architectural Record 4/1 (1894): 229-46 (Box 2)
  - Articles on campus architecture, Chris Drake, "The University of Chicago: Its Early Educational and Architectural Ideals," College of Wooster, 1985 (Box 2)
  - Maps, general (Box 3)
  - Maps, Campus Bike Map, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Maps, National Historic Landmarks, University of Chicago (Box 3)
  - Parking 1, "The University of Chicago Parking Structure, Summary of a Feasibility Report from Ralph H. Burke, Inc.," 1968 (Box 3)
  - Parking 2, "Traffic and Parking Plan," 1969 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook of Henry David Hubbard, ca. 1900 (Box 3)
  - Scrapbook of Henry David Hubbard, ca. 1900, 2 (Box 3)
  - Souvenir booklets, miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Souvenir booklets, The Buildings and Grounds of the University of Chicago, A Souvenir, 1892-1899 (Box 4)
  - Souvenir booklets, A. Wittemann, 1898 (Box 4)
  - Souvenir booklets, University of Chicago Weekly, 1899 (Box 4)
  - Souvenir booklets, color, ca. 1907 (Box 4)
  - Souvenir booklets, University of Chicago Press, 1908 (Box 4)
  - Souvenir booklets, 1914 (copy 1) (Box 5)
  - Souvenir booklets, 1914 (copy 2) (Box 5)
  - Souvenir booklets, 1916 (Box 5)
  - Souvenir booklets, University of Chicago Bookstore, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Souvenir booklets, 1921 (Box 5)
  - Souvenir booklets, 1921 (Box 5)
  - Souvenir, calendar, 1906 (Box 5)
  - Souvenir, calendar, 1913 (Box 5)
- Series II: Individual Buildings
  - Abbott Memorial Hall, 1 (Box 6)
  - Abbott Memorial Hall, 2 (Box 6)
  - Accelerator Building (Box 6)
  - Administration Building (Box 6)
  - American Bar Center (Box 6)
  - American Meat Institute Building (Box 6)
  - Argonne National Laboratory (Box 6)
  - Armour Clinical Research Building (Box 6)
  - Baptist Graduate Student Center (Rosenwald House) (Box 6)
  - Bartlett Gymnasium (Box 6)
  - Ben May Laboratory (Box 6)
  - Billings Hospital (Box 6)
  - Biological Sciences Learning Center and Jules F. Knapp Medical Research Center Complex (Box 7)
  - Black Oaks on Campus (Box 7)
  - Bobs Roberts Hospital (Box 7)
  - Bond Chapel (Box 7)
  - Breckinridge Hall (Box 7)
  - Burton-Judson Courts (Box 7)
  - Calvert House (Box 7)
  - A.J. Carlson Animal Research Laboratory (Box 7)
  - Center for Continuing Education, general (Box 8)
  - Center for Continuing Education, proposal (Box 8)
  - Center for International Studies (Box 8)
  - Chicago Theological Seminary (Box 8)
  - Classics Building (Box 8)
  - Cobb Hall, 1 (Box 9)
  - Cobb Hall, 2 (Box 9)
  - Cobb Hall, 3 (Box 9)
  - Cochrane-Woods Art Center/Smart Gallery (Box 9)
  - Council Tree Memorial Bench (Box 9)
  - Court Theater (Box 9)
  - Crerar Library, 1 (Box 9)
  - Crerar Library, 2 (Box 10)
  - Cummings Life Science Center (Box 10)
  - D'Evereux Hall (Box 10)
  - Disciples Divinity House (Box 10)
  - Duchossois Center for Advanced Medicine (Box 10)
  - East Madison Park (Box 10)
  - Eckhart Hall (Box 10)
  - Emmons Blaine Hall (Box 10)
  - Faculty Houses, 56th and Woodlawn (Box 10)
  - Field House (Box 11)
  - Foster Hall (Box 11)
  - Gerald Ratner Athletics Center (Box 11)
  - G.I. Housing (Box 11)
  - Goldblatt Magnetic Resonance Imaging Center (Box 11)
  - Goldblatt Memorial Hospital (Box 11)
  - Goodspeed Hall (Box 11)
  - Graduate School of Business, Hyde Park Center. (Box 11)
  - Green Hall (Box 11)
  - Greenwood Hall (Box 11)
  - Harper Memorial Library, general (Box 11)
  - Harper Memorial Library, cornerstone laying (Box 11)
  - Harper Memorial Library, dedication, 1 (Box 11)
  - Harper Memorial Library, dedication, 2 (Box 12)
  - Harper Memorial Library, dedication, 3 (Box 12)
  - Harper Memorial Library, PACE Associates study, 1960 (Box 12)
  - Harper Memorial Library, Rededication, 1973 (Box 12)
  - Haskell Hall (Box 13)
  - Hicks Memorial Hospital (Box 13)
  - Hinds Laboratory (Box 13)
  - Hitchcock Hall (Box 13)
  - Hospitals and clinics, general (Box 13)
  - Hull Court (Box 13)
  - Hutchinson Commons (Box 13)
  - Hyde Park-Kenwood Historic District (Box 13)
  - Ida Noyes Hall, 1 (Box 14)
  - Ida Noyes Hall, 2 (Box 14)
  - Ida Noyes Hall, 3 (Box 14)
  - Ida Noyes Hall, 4 (Box 14)
  - Ida Noyes Hall, 5 (Box 14)
  - Ida Noyes Hall, 6 (Box 14)
  - Industrial Relations Center (Charles S. Mott Building) (Box 15)
  - International House (Box 15)
  - Jackson Park (Box 15)
  - Jones Chemical Laboratory (Box 15)
  - Judd Hall (Box 15)
  - Kelly Hall (Box 15)
  - Kent Hall (Box 15)
  - Kenwood House (Box 15)
  - Kersten Physics Teaching Center (Box 16)
  - Kirsner Center for the Study of Digestive Diseases (Box 16)
  - Kovler Viral Oncology Laboratories (Box 16)
  - Laboratory for Astrophysics and Space Research (Box 16)
  - Law School, general (Box 16)
  - Law School, Laird Bell Quadrangle (Box 16)
  - Law School, Edward Douglas White Lecture Hall (Box 16)
  - Lexington Hall (Box 16)
  - Lillie House (Box 16)
  - Lying-In Hospital (Box 16)
  - MacLean, Norman Commons (Box 17)
  - Mandel Hall (Box 17)
  - Mansueto Library (Box 17)
  - McDonald Observatory (Box 17)
  - McLean Memorial Research Institute (formerly Argonne Cancer Research Hospital) (Box 17)
  - Midway Gardens (Box 17)
  - Midway Plaisance (Box 17)
  - Midway Studios (Box 17)
  - Mitchell Hospital and Rubloff Intensive Care Tower (Box 17)
  - Mitchell Tower (Box 18)
  - National Opinion Research Center (Box 18)
  - Nuclear Energy" Sculpture, by Henry Moore (Box 18)
  - Oriental Institute (Breasted Hall) (Box 18)
  - Oriental Institute (Dedication) (Box 18)
  - Orthogenic School (Box 18)
  - Paris Center (Box 18)
  - Phemister Hall (Box 18)
  - Pick Hall (Box 18)
  - Pierce Hall (Box 18)
  - President's House (Box 18)
  - Quadrangle Club (Box 18)
  - Rawson Laboratory, general (Box 19)
  - Rawson Laboratory, dedication (Box 19)
  - Rawson Laboratory, specifications (Box 19)
  - Regenstein Library, general, 1 (Box 19)
  - Regenstein Library, general, 2 (Box 19)
  - Regenstein Library, cornerstone laying and dedication (Box 20)
  - Regenstein Library, groundbreaking (Box 20)
  - Research Institutes, general (Box 20)
  - Residence halls, men, general (Box 20)
  - Residence halls, women, general (Box 20)
  - Reynolds Club (Box 20)
  - Robie House (Box 20)
  - Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, general, 1 (Box 21)
  - Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, general, 2 (Box 21)
  - Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, carillon (Box 21)
  - Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, cornerstone laying (Box 21)
  - Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, decoration (Box 21)
  - Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, dedication, 1928, 1 (Box 21)
  - Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, dedication, 1928, 2 (Box 22)
  - Rockefeller Memorial Chapel, rededication, 1988 (Box 22)
  - Rosenwald Hall (Box 22)
  - Ryerson Physical Laboratory (Box 22)
  - Sculpture (Box 22)
  - Searle Chemical Building (Box 22)
  - Shoreland Hall (Box 22)
  - Snell Hall (Box 22)
  - Social Science Research Building (Box 22)
  - Social Service Administration Building (Box 22)
  - Social Services Center (Box 22)
  - South Park (including Jackson Park, Midway Plaisance, and Washington Park) (Box 23)
  - Stagg Field (Box 23)
  - Steam Plant (Box 23)
  - Stuart Hall (Box 23)
  - Sunny Gymnasium (Box 23)
  - Surgery-Brain Research Pavilion (Box 23)
  - Swift Hall (Box 23)
  - University Church Disciples of Christ (Box 23)
  - University High School (Box 23)
  - University of Chicago Press Warehouse, Expansion Plan, 1971-1972 (Box 23)
  - Walker Museum (Box 23)
  - Whitman Laboratory (Box 23)
  - Wieboldt Hall (Box 24)
  - Wilder House (Box 24)
  - Woodward Court (Box 24)
  - Wyler Children's Hospital (Box 24)
  - Yerkes Observatory, 1 (Box 24)
  - Yerkes Observatory, 2 (Box 24)
  - Yerkes Observatory, 3 (Box 24)